University of Connecticut 1998.0276
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, School of Nursing Records
undated, 1938-2008
1998.0276
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
6.2 Linear feet
Records of the University of Connecticut School of Nursing, established in 1942 and accredited since 1943. The collection contains faculty meeting minutes, project documentation, photographs, multimedia and ephemeral materials. Further information is available from the School's website.
University of Connecticut. School of Nursing.
History
As early as 1937, public health personnel in the state explored the possibility of organizing courses for public health nurses at Connecticut State College but, lacking funds, the project was shelved. In 1940, a committee of 18 members was formed and in 1941 presented a report entitled "A School of Nursing for Connecticut." The proposal envisaged a program for registered nurses leading to the Bachelor of Science degree and a curriculum which would include 33 to 36 credits in required general courses plus a major in Nursing Education, School Nursing/Health Teaching or Public Health Nursing. The newly created University of Connecticut (named changed in 1939) Administration decided that a School of Nursing that would provide basic preparation in nursing as well as curricula for registered nurses would meet the need expressed in the report.
Students were admitted to the new School of Nursing as of September, 1942, although the School did not yet have a dean nor any nursing faculty. The first Dean, Carolyn Ladd Widmer, was appointed in July, 1942, and arrived on campus in August. Thirteen students entered the program in the Fall of 1942, 11 freshman and 2 sophomore transfers; nine of these students continued on to graduation.
Deans of the School have included: Carolyn Widner (1942-1967, Eleanor Gill (1967-1979, Marlene Kramer (1979-1988), Beverly Koerner (1989-1999), Laura Dzurec (2000-2007), Ann Bavier (2007- ).
[Note: Excerpted from Heritage of Accomplishment.]
General note
Published Works:
Heritage of Accomplishment. The History of the University of Connecticut School of Nursing, 1942-1981, University of Connecticut, circa 1990.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains faculty meeting minutes, project documentation, photographs, multimedia and ephemeral materials.
Arrangement
Series I: Inventory, ( undated, 1938-2008 )
Acquisition Information
Materials in the collection have been transferred sporadically from the School to the University Archives since the late 1980s.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to nursing education, leadership and the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
University of Connecticut. School of Nursing.; Administrative records; Audio visual materials; Correspondence; Interviews; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters; Notes; Nursing schools; Photocopies; Photographs; Press releases; Storrs (Conn.); Videocassettes
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1938-2008
  - Wellness Center (Box 1)
    - Final report, 1984
    - Interdisciplinary Nursing Technical Proposal, undated
    - Advisory Community, 1984-1988
    - Advisory Board Members, 1988-1990
    - Advisory Board meetings, 1980-1984
    - Statistics, 1982-1984
    - Correspondence, 1983-1984
    - Correspondence--Town of Mansfield, 1981-1982
    - Dardick, Kenneth, M.D., 1982
    - Fee schedule, undated
    - Health Advisory Committee, 1981
    - Interdisciplinary Nursing Practice Grant, 1981
    - Advisory Board, 1981-1984
    - Correspondence, 1981-1982
    - Meeting minutes, 1983-1984
    - Meeting minutes, 1981-1982
    - Grant--History, 1981-1982
    - Correspondence--Inquiries, 1982-1983
    - Funding, undated, 1983-1984
    - Team meetings, 1982-1984
    - Future funding--Town, 1982-1983
    - Federal Regulations, undated, 1976-1984
    - Fee for service, undated
    - Request for Proposals--Innovative Nursing Practice Arrangements, undated, 1986
    - Correspondence--Legislative, 1982-1985
    - Advisory Committee minutes, 1981
    - Student evaluations, undated
    - Contract proposal, 1984
    - Space/Furnishings, 1981-1984
    - Space, 1981
    - Dr. Keiser, 1977-1983
    - Correspondence, 1981-1984
    - Forms, undated
    - Team meetings, 1981-1983
    - Progress reports
      - 1981 May 28 - August 28
      - 1981 August 29 - 1982 January 14
      - 1982 January 15 - April 27
      - 1982 April 27 - July 27
      - 1982 July 27 - Ocotber 27
      - 1982 October 27 - 1983 January 27
      - 1982 January 28 - April 28
      - 1983 April 28 - July 28
      - 1983 July 28 - October 28
      - 1983 October 28 - 1984 January 28
  - Box 2
    - Dolan Room, undated
    - Alumni awards, 1997, 1999
    - Photographs, undated
    - Logo, undated
    - Photographs, undated, 1947-1994
    - Dolan Collection publicity, 1995-1996
    - Museum--History of Nursing, 1959-1976
    - Packard, Sheila, 1995
    - Health Center, 1971-1974
    - Widmer, Carolyn, undated, 1961-1966
    - Gill, Eleanor, undated, 1938-1990
    - Koerner, Beverly, 1972, 1988
    - Redman, Barbara, undated, 1995
    - Dzurec, Laura, 2000
    - Distinguished Lecture series, 1996, 1999
    - Distinguished Alumni Banquet, 1998
    - Instructional Media Laboratory, 1975
    - Relocation/Merger, 1983-1994
    - Ph.D. Prograom, undated, 1991-1994
    - Wellness Center (photographs, postcards, slides, etc.), 1981-1983
  - Box 3
    - Faculty meeting minutes
      - 1942-1948
      - 2004
      - 2005
      - 2006
      - 2007
      - 2008
    - Nursing Education in Alcohol and other Drug Abuse (NEADA) Project, 1991
      - Curriculum Plan and Schemata
      - Graduate Module I, Handout Masters
      - Graduate Module II, Handout Masters
      - Instructor's Guide
      - Undergraduate Module III, Instructor's Guide
      - Instructor's Guide (final draft)
      - Publicity
    - "Our Dream," Song of TPU, by Kathy Patusky, undated
    - History of Move, 1962-1983
    - Move Study, 1983
    - Move, 1984
    - Gill, Eleanor Photograph, undated
  - Multimedia (Box 4)
    - 3 U-Matic Video cassettes, undated
      General note
      Interviews with Deans Widmer, Gill and Kramer
    - 5 inch reel to reel audio tape (Pomp and Circumstance), indated
    - 23 7 inch reel to reel audio tapes, undated, 1958-1974
      Topics: unknown, Nurses convocation, Capping, Programmed Learning, WTIC, CNA Professional Nursing Education Study Committee meeting.
  - White Caps Scrapbook, 1944-1947 (Box 5)